I was only four years old
كان عمري أربع سنوات
when I saw my mother load a washing machine
عندما رأيت والدتي تضع الملابس في الغسالة
for the very first time in her life.
للمرة الاولى في حياتها
That was a great day for my mother.
لقد كان يوماً رائعاً لوالدتي
My mother and father had been saving money for years
كان والدي ووالدتي يدخرون المال لهذا اليوم منذ سنوات
to be able to buy that machine,
لكي يستطيعوا شراء هذه الغسالة
and the first day it was going to be used,
وفي اول يوم لاستخدامها
even Grandma was invited
دعيت جدتي لحضور ذلك الحدث
to see the machine.
لكي ترى هذه الآلة
And Grandma was even more excited.
وكانت جدتي متحمسة جداً
Throughout her life
لقد كان الغسيل لديها يعني
she had been heating water with firewood,
تسخين المياه على نار الاخشاب
and she had hand washed laundry
ومن ثم البدء بالغسل اليدوي
for seven children.
لسبعة اطفال
And now she was going to watch
والان هي تشاهد
electricity do that work.
الكهرباء تقوم بهذا العمل
My mother carefully opened the door,
اذكر عندما فتحت والدتي باب الغسالة بهدوء
and she loaded the laundry
ووضعت الغسيل
into the machine,
داخل الغسالة
like this.
هكذا
And then, when she closed the door,
ومن ثم اغلقت الباب
Grandma said, "No, no, no, no.
فقالت جدتي . لا .. لا .. لا
Let me, let me push the button."
دعيني انا اضغط زر التشغيل
And Grandma pushed the button,
وضغط جدتي زر التشغيل
and she said, "Oh, fantastic!
ومن ثم قالت " رائع ..
I want to see this! Give me a chair!
اريد ان اشاهد العملية بأكملها .. احضروا لي كرسياً
Give me a chair! I want to see it,"
احضروا لي كرسياً .. اريد ان اشاهد "
and she sat down in front of the machine,
وجلست امام الغسالة
and she watched the entire washing program.
وشاهدت عملية الغسل بأكملها
She was mesmerized.
لقد فتنت حينها بهذه الآلة ..
To my grandmother,
بالنسبة لجدتي ..
the washing machine was a miracle.
كانت تلك الآلة معجزة
Today, in Sweden and other rich countries,
اليوم .. في السويد .. وفي الدول الغنية
people are using
الناس تستخدم
so many different machines.
العديد من الآلات
Look, the homes are full of machines.
المنازل مليئة بالآلات
I can't even name them all.
لدرجة انه لا يمكنني ان احصيهم
And they also, when they want to travel,
كما اننا يمكننا ان ننتقل الى اي مكان في هذا
they use flying machines
العالم باستخدام الات طائرة "الطائرات"
that can take them to remote destinations.
والتي يمكنها حملهم الى وجهات نائية
And yet, in the world, there are so many people
ورغم كل هذا .. هناك مناطق في هذا العالم
who still heat the water on fire,
يقطنها اشخاص يقومون بتسخين المياه على الحطب
and they cook their food on fire.
ويطبخون اطعمتهم على الحطب
Sometimes they don't even have enough food,
واحيانا لا يملكون الطعام الكافي
and they live below the poverty line.
وهم يعيشون تحت خط الفقر
There are two billion fellow human beings
وهناك ما يقارب ملياري شخص
who live on less than two dollars a day.
يعيشون باقل من دولارين يومياً
And the richest people over there --
الاغنياء هناك ..
there's one billion people --
يبلغ عددهم مليار ..
and they live above what I call the "air line,"
انا اطلق عليهم .. من يعيش فوق خط " الطيران "
because they spend more than $80 a day
لانهم ينفقون مايقارب 80 دولار يومياً
on their consumption.
على المستهلكات
But this is just one, two, three billion people,
ولكن هؤلاء فحسب 3 مليارات شخص
and obviously there are seven billion people in the world,
وهناك ما يقارب 7 مليارات شخص في هذا الكوكب
so there must be one, two, three, four billion people more
لذا لابد من وجود 4 مليار شخص
who live in between the poverty and the air line.
يعيشون فوق خط الفقر .. واسفل خط " الطيران "
They have electricity,
هم حتماً يملكون الكهرباء ..
but the question is, how many have washing machines?
ولكن السؤال هو .. كم عدد من يملك غسالة ملابس منهم ؟
I've done the scrutiny of market data,
لقد قمت بدراسة معمقة للسوق
and I've found that, indeed,
ووجدت
the washing machine has penetrated below the air line,
ان خط " الغسيل الكهربائي " يقع اسف خط " الطيران "
and today there's an additional one billion people out there
ويوجد اليوم مليار شخص
who live above the "wash line."
يعيشون فوق خط " الغسيل الكهربائي "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they consume more than $40 per day.
وهم يصرفون ما يقارب 40 دولار يومياً
So two billion have access to washing machines.
اذا هناك في العالم ملياري شخص يستخدمون الغسالات الكهربائية
And the remaining five billion,
ولكن ماذا عن الـ 5 مليارات المتبقية ..
how do they wash?
كيف تغسل ملابسها ؟
Or, to be more precise,
دعوني اصيغ العبارة بصورة أخرى ..
how do most of the women in the world wash?
كيف تغسل معظم النسوة في العالم ملابس عائلاتها ؟
Because it remains hard work for women to wash.
لان الغسيل يُعد من المهام الصعبة التي تقوم بها النساء
They wash like this: by hand.
انهم يغسلون هكذا .. باليدين !
It's a hard, time-consuming labor,
انه امرٌ صعب .. انها مهمة شاقة
which they have to do for hours every week.
عليهم ان يقوموا بها لساعات كل اسبوع
And sometimes they also have to bring water from far away
واحيانا .. يتوجب عليهم احضار المياه من اماكن بعيدة
to do the laundry at home,
لكي يقوموا بالغسل داخل المنزل
or they have to bring the laundry away to a stream far off.
او ان يأخذوا غسيلهم الى مجرى المياه
And they want the washing machine.
واعتقد انهم يرغبون بشراء غسالة الملابس
They don't want to spend such a large part of their life
فهم لا يريدون ان يقضوا فترة طويلة من عمرهم
doing this hard work
وهم يقومون بهذا العمل المضني ..
with so relatively low productivity.
وبهذه الانتاجية المنخفضة
And there's nothing different in their wish
وامنيتهم تلك لا تختلف
than it was for my grandma.
عن امنية جدتي
Look here, two generations ago in Sweden --
انظروا .. منذوا جيلين في السويد ..
picking water from the stream,
كانوا يحملون المياه من المصدر
heating with firewood and washing like that.
ويقومون باشعال النيران اسفلها ويغسلون الملابس هكذا ..
They want the washing machine in exactly the same way.
وكانوا يريدون الغسالة بشدة .. كما يريدوها هؤلاء الناس ..
But when I lecture to environmentally-concerned students,
وعندما عرضت هذا على طلابي المهتمين بالامور البيئية
they tell me, "No, everybody in the world cannot have cars and washing machines."
قالوا لي " لا .. لا يمكن للجميع في العالم ان يملك سيارات وغسالات "
How can we tell this woman
كيف يمكننا ان نخبر هذه المرأة ..
that she ain't going to have a washing machine?
انها لن تحصل على غسالة ملابس ؟
And then I ask my students,
ومن ثم سئلت طلابي ..
I've asked them -- over the last two years I've asked,
سئلتهم .. على مدى السنتين الماضيتين ..
"How many of you doesn't use a car?"
" كم واحد منكم لم يستخدم سيارة ؟ "
And some of them proudly raise their hand
وبعضهم بكل فخر رفعوا ايديهم ..
and say, "I don't use a car."
وقالوا " نحن لا نستخدم سيارة "
And then I put the really tough question:
ومن ثم سئلت سؤالاً اشد صعوبة ..
"How many of you
" كم واحد منكم ..
hand-wash your jeans and your bed sheets?"
غسل بنطاله الجينز او ملاءة السرير بيديه ؟ "
And no one raised their hand.
ولم يرفع احدٌ يده ..
Even the hardcore in the green movement
حتى من هم في صلب الحركة البيئية .. والمتعصبين للبيئة
use washing machines.
يستخدمون الغسالات الكهربائية ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So how come [this is] something that everyone uses
إذا .. لماذا هذا الشيء يستخدمه الجميع ..
and they think others will not stop it? What is special with this?
ويعلمون ان لا احد قد يغنيهم عن ذلك .. ما المميز في هذا ؟
I had to do an analysis about the energy used in the world.
كان علي ان اقوم بتحليل عن استخدام الطاقة في العالم ..
Here we are.
ها نحن ..
Look here, you see the seven billion people up there:
انظروا هنا .. انظروا الى 7 مليارات شخص
the air people, the wash people,
جماعة الطيران .. جماعة الغسيل الكهربائي
the bulb people and the fire people.
جماعة المصباح الكهربائي .. جماعة النار
One unit like this
واحدة كهذه ..
is an energy unit of fossil fuel --
هي وحدة طاقة من الوقود العضوي
oil, coal or gas.
النفط .. الفحم .. الغاز الطبيعي
That's what most of electricity and the energy in the world is.
وهو - الوقود الطبيعي - مصدر معظم الكهرباء في هذا العالم
And it's 12 units used in the entire world,
و12 وحدة تستخدم في العالم ككل
and the richest one billion, they use six of them.
والمليار الاغنى في العالم يستخدم 6 واحدات منها
Half of the energy is used by one seventh of the world's population.
نصف الطاقة في العالم يستهلكها سبع سكانه
And these ones who have washing machines,
وهؤلاء الذين يملكون الغسالة الكهربائية
but not a house full of other machines,
دون بقية اللات المنزلية
they use two.
يستخدمون وحدتين
This group uses three, one each.
وهذه المجموعة تستخدم 3 وحدات .. واحدة لكل منها ..
And they also have electricity.
ويملكون الكهرباء
And over there they don't even use one each.
والناس هناك .. لا يستخدمون اي وحدة
That makes 12 of them.
وهذا مجموعه 12 وحدة
But the main concern
ولكن القلق الاكبر
for the environmentally-interested students -- and they are right --
للطلاب المهتمين بالبيئة .. وهم محقون
is about the future.
هو فيما يخص المستقبل
What are the trends? If we just prolong the trends,
ماهي مناحي المستقبل .. كيف ستتغير
without any real advanced analysis, to 2050,
حسناً .. لننظر الى 2050 .. بدون تحليل معمق ..
there are two things that can increase the energy use.
نحن نعي ان اي زيادة في استهلاك الطاقة لها سببين
First, population growth.
الاول هو النمو السكاني
Second, economic growth.
والثاني هو النمو الاقتصادي
Population growth will mainly occur among the poorest people here
ان النمو السكاني سوف يحدث في الغالب في المجتمعات الفقيرة
because they have high child mortality
لانها تملك نسبة الانجاب الاعلى في العالم
and they have many children per woman.
وهم ينجبون كثيراً من الاطفال
And [with] that you will get two extra,
اي سوف نحصل على مليارين جديدين
but that won't change the energy use very much.
ولكن بدون زيادة في الاستهلاك فيما يخص الطاقة
What will happen is economic growth.
ماذا سيحدث فيما يخص النمو الاقتصادي
The best of here in the emerging economies --
ان ما سيحدث يما يخص الاقتصاديات النامية
I call them the New East --
الذين ادعوهم الشرق الجديد
they will jump the air line.
هو انهم سوف يقفزون الى خط الطيران
"Wopp!" they will say.
"هووب" هكذا سيقولون ..
And they will start to use as much as the Old West are doing already.
وسوف يبدأون بالاستهلاك كما يفعل الغرب القديم اليوم
And these people, they want the washing machine.
وهؤلاء الاشخاص يريدون غسالات الملابس ..
I told you. They'll go there.
انا متأكد .. سوف يصلون هنا .
And they will double their energy use.
وسوف يتضاعف استهلاكهم من الطاقة
And we hope that the poor people will get into the electric light.
ونحن نأمل ان الفقراء سوف تصلهم الكهرباء .. لاستخدام المصابيح
And they'll get a two-child family without a stop in population growth.
وسوف ينجبون طفلين في كل عائلة .. دون ان يقلل ذلك من النمو السكاني
But the total energy consumption
وسيغدو الاستهلاك الكلي للطاقة
will increase to 22 units.
مايقارب 22 وحدة
And these 22 units --
وهذه الـ 22 وحدة
still the richest people use most of it.
سيبقى الاغنياء هم من يستخدمون الحصة الاكبر منها
So what needs to be done?
اذا مالذي يجب القيام به حيال هذا .؟
Because the risk,
بسبب الخطر من التغير المناخي
the high probability of climate change is real.
والذي هو حتمي ..
It's real.
حتمي
Of course they must be more energy-efficient.
حتماً يتوجب علينا ان نزيد من فاعلية استخدام الطاقة
They must change behavior in some way.
يجب ان نغير من السلوكيات بصورة ما
They must also start to produce green energy,
علينا ان نبدأ بانتاج طاقات نظيفة
much more green energy.
الكثير من الطاقات النظيفة
But until they have the same energy consumption per person,
ولكن حتى يصبح معدل استخدام للطاقة متساوي مع الجميع !
they shouldn't give advice to others --
لا يتوجب عليهم ان يعطوا نصائح .. للآخرين
what to do and what not to do.
عما يجب و ما لا يجب القيام به !
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
Here we can get more green energy all over.
هنا يمكننا ان ننتج طاقة نظيفة بصورة عامة
This is what we hope may happen.
هذا ما نأمله ..
It's a real challenge in the future.
انه تحد كبير في المستقبل
But I can assure you that this woman in the favela in Rio,
ولكني أؤكد لكم .. ان هذه المرأة في ريو دي جانيرو
she wants a washing machine.
تريد غسالة ملابس كهربائية
She's very happy about her minister of energy
انها سعيدة بوزراة الطاقة في دولتها ..
that provided electricity to everyone --
ان الطاقة ستتوفر للجميع ..
so happy that she even voted for her.
انها سعيدة لانها صوتت لهذه البطلة ..
And she became Dilma Rousseff,
لقد غدت " ديلما روسيف "
the president-elect
الرئيسة المنتخبة ..
of one of the biggest democracies in the world --
في دولة من اكبر الديموقراطيات في العالم
moving from minister of energy to president.
لقد انتقلت من وزاة الكهرباء " الطاقة " .. الى الرئاسة ..
If you have democracy,
ان اي دولة ديموقراطية ..
people will vote for washing machines.
سوف يصوت شعبها للحصول على " غسالة ملابس "
They love them.
انهم يحبونها ..
And what's the magic with them?
ما السحري في هذه الآلة ؟
My mother explained the magic with this machine
لقد شرحت لي والدتي السحر في هذه الآلة ...
the very, very first day.
منذ اليوم الاول ..
She said, "Now Hans,
قالت لي " هانس ..
we have loaded the laundry.
كل ما علينا فعله هو وضع الغسيل .. في هذه الآلة
The machine will make the work.
وهي سوف تقوم بالعمل
And now we can go to the library."
والآن يمكننا الذهاب الى المكتبة "
Because this is the magic:
هذا هو السحر ..
you load the laundry,
تضع الملابس في الآلة ..
and what do you get out of the machine?
وتحصل في المقابل على ...
You get books out of the machines,
تحصل على الكتب من هذه الآلة ..
children's books.
كتب الاطفال ..
And mother got time to read for me.
استطاعت والدتي .. ان تقرأ لي ..
She loved this. I got the "ABC's" --
لقد احبت هذا .. لقد علمتني الاحرف ..
this is where I started my career as a professor,
وهكذا غدوت " استاذا "
when my mother had time to read for me.
كانت والدتي تملك الوقت لكي تقرأ لي " تُعلمني "
And she also got books for herself.
لقد قرأت كتب خاصة بها ..
She managed to study English
استطاعت ان تدرس اللغة الانجليزية ..
and learn that as a foreign language.
استطاعت ان تتعلم لغات أجنبية ..
And she read so many novels,
قرأت الكثير من الروايات ..
so many different novels here.
الكثير منها ..
And we really, we really loved this machine.
وهذا ما أحببناه فيما يخص هذه الآلة ..
And what we said, my mother and me,
ونحن نقول - انا ووالدتي -
"Thank you industrialization.
شكراً للحركة الصناعية ..
Thank you steel mill.
شكراً للتعدين ..
Thank you power station.
شكراً لمحطة الكهرباء ..
And thank you chemical processing industry
وشكراً للصناعات الكيميائية
that gave us time to read books."
التي أعطتنا وقتاً لقراءة الكتب
Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)